A Guide to the Papers of Henry James, 1855-1969, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
  - Subseries C: Other Correspondents
    - [Fanny Mecker] to "My dear Gray," 1869 October 16, ALs, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:71)
      * Fanny Mecker letter: James embodies the belief that is satisfying to the heart and intellect. The truth of the Divine Natural Humanity or the Lord is manifest in the flesh. My life is served daily from this eternal Spring. * Anonymous letter: Discusses Henry James under the pledge of secrecy. James is a great man. Seems to delight in the mysteries of women. His philosophy is an easy one: a virtuous woman is a myth and the prostitution of women in not owing to mind but wants of the stomach and something lower, and can be taught to gratify their desires with the same impunity that men do. Never intended to marry but was forced to. Last winter he had a woman where he could put his hand on and off her for a long while, then introduced her to the mysteries, he says, "to her infinite delight." Discusses details of his various women. Writer has letters, which proves all he says. * C. Robinson, September 1869: Has obtained the correspondence he mentioned. Meet him at any point on the R.R. * J. C. Hathaway, September 18, 1869: Have the document which was copied. If any inquiries are made, keep dark. If he has to write to anyone employ an amanuensis. P.S. Please get some one to copy letter of C. Robinson. Don't copy it yourself. Attached to a group of handwritten documents entitled, "Social Studies 1869," regarding Henry James Sr., including notes by J. C. Hathwawy, C. Robinson, and an anonymous letter discussing the James' philosophy of the nature of women. #6251-bc
    - R. J. Nevin to Grace Carter, 1894 January 28, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:72)
      Funeral can be Wednesday at cemetery. Hay has wired Henry James. Asked for size of coffin for proper building of vault. They secured a lot near Shelley's grave and close to Mrs. [Stroup?]. #6251-ac
    - R. J. Nevin to Grace [Carter], 1894 February 7, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 9:73)
      Sorry, her bag has not been found. Given police information and they feel case hopeless. Sympathy for her. Her presence in Venice could not have prevented final catastrophe. No doubt Woolson's falling was accidental. She fainted before she fell. #6251-ac
    - R. J. Nevin to [Grace] Carter, n.y. June 30, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:74)
      Just in from making sick calls. No sign of her bag. There is an office at the Capitol where lost things are taken. #6251-ac
    - LeRoy Phillips to [Edna] Kenton, 1950 January 8, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:75)
      Appreciates her tireless research. Her penetrating intuitions continue to result in disclosures undreamed of at the beginning of the century. Thanks for the gift of Eight Uncollected Tales of Henry James. #6251-m
    - LeRoy Phillips to [Edna] Kenton, 1951 January 1, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:76)
      In anticipation awaits Eight Uncollected Tales of Henry James. Noticed a recent review of Eight Uncollected Tales of Henry James in The New Yorker. Pleased that he has done anything to help in this Jamesian criticism and research. He enjoys the friendship of her colleagues, Donald Brien and Leon Edel. P.S. Allan Wade feels he wasn't correctly cited by her in the article, The Seer's Art, in The Atlantic Monthly. #6251-m
    - LeRoy Phillips to [Edna] Kenton, 1951 January 6, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:77)
      Thanks for the gift and the clarifying notes. Discusses the possibility of Henry James collaborating on an article, but he has no evidence beyond the Atlantic Monthly Index. #6251-m
    - Mary [Shelvin?] to Edna Kenton, 1953 June 17, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with enclosure. (Box-folder 9:78)
      Forwarding the royalty from Eight Uncollected Tales of Henry James for the period ending April 30, 1953. #6251-m
    - Marie L. Thompson to "Dear Madam" [Grace Carter], 1894 February 5, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:79)
      Sympathy letter at the loss of her cousin Mrs. C. F. Woolson. Heard Constance speak often of them all. Loved and admired her. Grace Carter's name and most of leading families in Cooperstown familiar to her. #6251-ac
    - [unknown] to Lincoln Kirstein, 1939 June 1, TL copy, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:80)
      Has been talking to Edna Kenton about her Henry James work. Kenton would like to get her complete work on him out by the centenary of Henry James's birth. Should be a monumental piece of great importance. The problem, though, is of finances. Looking for anyone who would want to contribute to the project. Nelson Rockefellor? #6251-m
    - Allan Wade to [Edna] Kenton, 1950 October 29, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:81)
      Excuse his discourtesy for not writing earlier about her gift of Eight Uncollected Tales of Henry James. Great delight to have all of James's fiction on his shelves. Interested in her introduction. She has a wonderful memory for all the details in James's many writings. #6251-m
    - Allan Wade to [Edna] Kenton, 1950 December 5, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:82)
      Hopes that she could add something to her collection of Jamesiana. Doesn't think the essay is very good, except for perhaps beginners in James. [Essay not present] #6251-m
    - Hugh Walpole to "The Editor [of] The Bookman," 1923 October 18, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:83)
      Replying to enquiry about ghost stories. If a ghost story succeeds in making his flesh creep, it has succeeded. There is a renewed interest rather than belief in spirit phenomena. The most convincing ghost story he has ever read was The Turn of the Screw by Henry James. #6251-m
    - Phil Young to Leon [Edel], 1955 January 10, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:84)
      Sorry it turned out the way it did, but the only way he would do it would be to debate it or not do it at all. However, it is not a personal debate. Doesn't like being away from New York, but likes the Department at Kansas very much. Looking for volume two of the Henry James biography. #6251-bi
    - Phil Young to Leon [Edel], 1955 January 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:85)
      Thanks for note which is a relief. No longer has a copy of his piece, but guesses that he wasn't entirely clear, or, at any rate, left it open for misreading. #6251-bi
  - Series III: Miscellaneous Manuscripts and Documents
    - "Black and White," 1893 January 12, pp. 39-40. (Box-folder 9:86)
      Brief article (p. 40) discussing poor reception at St. James's Theatre of Henry James's play. In Oversize box W-5. #6251-ak
    - Satirical description of "A Plain Tale" by Henry James, [1902 January-February], printed fragment, 1 item. (Box-folder 9:87)
      From The Book Lover. #6251-ad
    - Invitation to the Grolier Club Henry James Exhibit, 1946 November 21, D. (Box-folder 9:88)
    - Notes made from the files of the George D. Sproul edition of Shakespeare's Complete Works, [1952], TMs, 2 p. on 2 l. (Box-folder 9:89)
      #6251-ad
    - Interview with Alvin L. Coburn regarding Henry James, [1953 July 17], TMs, 10 pp. on 10 l. (Box-folder 9:90)
      Original located in Barrett personal papers. #6526-f
    - Miscellaneous Documents: dealers' descriptions and envelopes which contained original James material, 1955 August 24. (Box-folder 10:1)
    - Vaccination booklet of Mrs. Rosalind Roberts, 1964 March 4, DS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 10:2)
    - Introductory Address by Cliffton Waller Barrett presenting Montgomery Hyde at the Grolier Club, n.d., AMs, 5 pp. on 5 l. (Box-folder 10:3)
    - Notes by LeRoy Phillips on the Scribner's prospectus of The Novels and Tales of Henry James, n.d., AMs, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 10:4)
    - Notes regarding Henry James, Sr., n.d., AMss, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 10:5)
      Notes written on the outside covers of two envelopes which held articles or documents. One envelope is entitled, 1869: The Secret of Henry James of Boston and the other envelope is entitled, A Dead Man's Secret: Henry James.
    - Christmas Greeting, n.d., D, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 10:6)
      #6251-ac
    - Book Jackets for The Outcry and The Finer Grain by Henry James, n.d., photocopies, 2 items. (Box-folder 10:7)
      #6251-ak
    - Der Amerikaner and Daisy Miller: Un Episode International, n.d., 2 negatives. (Box-folder 10:8)
      Images are of the front covers of James's International publications. #6251-ak
  - Series IV: Photographs and Portraits
    - Pencil Portrait of Henry James by William James, 1861, 1 item. (Box-folder 10:9)
      Framed portrait. Oversize box R-1. #6251-aq
    - Henry James, [ca. 1890's?], 1 photograph, mounted. (Box-folder 10:10)
      Inscribed by Henry James: "To Douglas Ainslie in very friendly remembrance" #6251-bd
    - Henry James, [ca. 1898], 1 photograph. (Box-folder 10:11)
      Inscribed by Henry James: "Yours till death." Includes 8x10 reproduction and a printed reproduction appearing on "Supplement to Literature, April 20, 1898." #6251-g
    - Henry James, 1899 August, 1 photograph. (Box-folder 10:12)
      Photograph from Cora Crane's "Oxenbridges" scrapbook. #5505-e
    - Portrait of Henry James, [ca. 1908], 1 framed item. (Box-folder 10:13)
      Portrait of Henry James at "Age 65." Three photographic reproductions in folder. [Location to be determined by Greg]. #6251
    - "Henry James in Witness Box" by Max Beerbohm, [ca. 1908], 1 original pencil drawing with various reproductions. (Box-folder 10:14)
      Includes brochure for the Annual Meeting of the Gleeson Library Associates, University of San Francisco, March 22, 1970, which used image for brochure cover. #6251-k
    - Henry James, [1913 March], 2 photographs. (Box-folder 10:15)
      Two copies of the Supplement to The Bookman with photograph attached. #6251-ak, #7436-a
    - Henry James, [1913 July], 1 photograph. (Box-folder 10:16)
      Photograph by E. O. Hoppe. Inscribed by Henry James: "To his friend Price Collins." Oversize box W-5. #6251
    - Henry James, wearing top hat, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 10:17)
      Printed reproduction: "Courtesy, Charles Scribner's Sons." #6251-m
    - Henry James, seated, holding document, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 10:18)
      #6251-m
    - Portrait of Henry James by John Singer Sargent, n.d., 1 photograph, mounted. (Box-folder 10:19)
      Photograph of portrait with John Singer Sargent's autograph below photograph. Oversize W-5. #6663
    - Two portraits of Henry James by John Singer Sargent, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 10:20)
      One photograph and one reprint of John Singer Sargent's sketches. #6251-ak
    - Portrait of Henry James by William James, n.d., 1 photograph. (Box-folder 10:21)
      Original at the Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum, Boston, Massachusetts. By William James, nephew of Henry James. #6251-ak
    - Henry James with Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, n.d., 1 published photograph. (Box-folder 10:22)
      Caption below photograph: "Mrs. Ward and Henry James in the Garden at Stocks. From a photograph by Miss Dorothy Ward." #6251-ak
    - Henry James and Mrs. Humphrey Ward, n.d., 1 photograph. (Box-folder 10:23)
      Includes ANS by D. M. Ward, "With kind regards as promised." #6251-ak
    - Henry James and Cora Crane, n.d., 1 photograph. (Box-folder 10:24)
    - Henry James, n.d., 1 postcard. (Box-folder 10:25)
      Photograph by Alice Boughton/Library of Congress. #7267-a
    - Portrait of Henry James by Jacques-Emile Blanche, n.d., published reprints, 3 copies. (Box-folder 10:26)
    - Pencil sketch of Henry James by W. R. [William Rothenstein], n.d., 2 copies. (Box-folder 10:27)
    - Portrait of a young Henry James, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 10:28)
      From the portrait by John La Farge. Book-jacket of Henry James by Bruce R. McElderry.
    - Henry James busts, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 10:29)
      One image includes caption: "Henry James from a bronze by Derwent Wood in the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge." The second image is of bust in the Tate Gallery, London. #6251-ak
    - Henry James: Miscellaneous portraits and photographs, n.d., 7 items. (Box-folder 10:30)
    - "Mr. Henry James in London" by Max Beerbohm, n.d., 1 cartoon with facsimile of speech. (Box-folder 10:31)
      Oversize box W-5. #6251-m
    - "Henry James Revisiting America" by Max Beerbohm, n.d., 1 cartoon with facsimile of speech. (Box-folder 10:32)
    - Drawing Room of Barbaro, n.d., 1 photograph. (Box-folder 10:33)
      With inscription by Henry James on verso of photograph. #6251-g
    - Lamb House, n.d., 1 photograph. (Box-folder 10:34)
      With inscription by [Henry James] on verso: "A bit of the garden of Lamb House trying to look alluring." #6251-ac
    - Miscellaneous photographs of Lamb House and James's gravestone, n.d. (Box-folder 10:35)
    - Henry James's desk at Lamb House, n.d., 1 photograph. (Box-folder 10:36)
      With note on back in unknown hand: "James's desk at Lamb House, Rye, which contained the secreted wallet (now in the Barrett Collection) found by Dan Laurence." [Wallet not in collection] #6251-ad
    - Miscellaneous photographs of persons and places associated with Henry James, n.d., 6 images, 8 items. (Box-folder 10:37)
      Includes photographs of Edmund Gosse [?]. #6251-au
    - Ink sketch of Henry James, Sr., n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 10:38)
    - Dr. Baldwin, n.d., 1 photograph. (Box-folder 10:39)
      Dr. Baldwin was a friend of Henry James and an American expatriate in Florence, Italy. #6251-m